Guide to the Archives of Irish America Collection of Irish Institute of New York AIA.020
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Collection of Irish Institute of New York
1950-2018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Institute of New York
Morrissey, Kevin
United Irish Foundation
AIA.020
7.8 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 oversize folder
37.2 Megabytes in 24 images
The Irish Institute of New York, originally known as the American Irish Feis Institute, is a non-profit organization dedicated to cultural and philanthropic endeavors since 1950. The collection consists of meeting minutes, correspondence, annual dinner programs and speeches, brochures, financial reports, and committee information.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series as follows:
Series I. American Irish Feis Institute, 1950-1959 Series II. General and Administrative Files, 1950-2018 Series III. Financial Records, 1953-1997 Series IV. Audio Materials, 1960 Series V. United Irish Foundation Records, 1982-2004
The original order of the material was maintained. Material in the 2016 accretion in Series II and V has not been arranged by an archivist and is arranged in the order in which it was received from the donor. Material in the 2018 accretion was added to Series II in boxes 7-11.
Historical Note
The Irish Institute of New York was founded in 1950 as the American Irish Feis Institute by County Mayo native Paul O'Dwyer. It is a non-profit organization dedicated to cultural and philanthropic endeavors. The Institute's building on West 48th Street served as the headquarters for scores of Irish organizations between 1952 and 1982. Since 1960 the Institute has distributed more than one million dollars to non-profit organizations in both the United States (US) and Ireland.
The American Irish Feis Institute was created in 1950 to establish a center for Irish activities in New York. The founders included Paul O'Dwyer, Sean Keating, Joseph F. McLoughlin, James FitzPatrick, Patrick Corley, Michael Mullvaney, William B. Burke, John Niblo, Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, and other prominent members of the New York Irish community. Their goal was to promote Irish culture and provide financial support for fledgling projects both in the US and Ireland. The organization officially changed its name to the Irish Institute of New York, Inc. three years later. In 1952, under the leadership of its board chairman, Paul O'Dwyer, the Institute purchased a building at 326 West 48th Street in New York City to serve as their Irish center. For almost thirty years, this building was headquarters to hundreds of Irish American organizations who paid little or no rent.
During its early years, the Institute was plagued with financial worries. The Institute tried a variety of fundraising schemes, including charter tours to Ireland and an annual fundraising dinner, the latter which proved most successful. With the political connections of Mayor William O'Dwyer and other public officials, the Institute was able to feature such figures as Congressman Charles Buckley (D-NY), and Senator John F. Kennedy (D-MA) as honored guests at the annual dinner. By 1960, the Institute had paid off its mortgage and began to establish its grant fund. The first grant was awarded that year to the Irish Arts Council in Dublin in the amount of $5,000. In 1966, the Institute contributed $150,000 to the John F. Kennedy Memorial Arboretum in Wexford as a memorial to the late president and an attempt to aid Ireland's reforestation project.
The Institute was forced to sell the original building at West 48th Street in 1982 due to rising costs and a decreasing New York Irish population. A result of this sale, however, was an increase the Institute's grant awards. Grants in excess of $100,000 were made to the Irish American Cultural Institute for scholarship purposes and to the New York Irish History Roundtable to commission the publication, The New York Irish, edited by Ronald H. Bayor and Timothy Meagher, a collection of scholarly essays published in 1996.
Since 1990 the Irish Institute has supported the work of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center and its predecessor, the Irish Immigration Reform Movement (with grants totaling more than $75,000), as well as Glucksman Ireland House at New York University, the Pat Finucane Centre in Derry and the Conway Mill Project in West Belfast.
Custodial History
The material in this collection consists of accessions from two officers of the Irish Institute. Material on the Institute's early years was acquired as part of the Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Collection and separated in 1996. Cudahy was the first secretary of the Irish Institute and a life-long friend of founder Paul O'Dwyer. In 2001 Kevin Morrissey donated materials covering the years 1966-1982 which had been turned over to him when he was elected President of the Irish Institute. In 2005, John Garvey donated four reel-to-reel audio tapes from the Annual Dinner of the Irish Institute of New York, 12 March 1960. The 2016 accretion was picked up from Kevin Morrissey by Marion Casey in August 2016 and transferred to the Tamiment Library in November 2016.
The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.048 and 2016.070.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the work of the Irish Institute of New York and its charitable programs. Material includes meeting minutes, correspondence, annual dinner programs and speeches, brochures, financial reports, committee information, digital and print photographs, grant applications, and reports on programs funded through the Institute.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accretions were donated by Kevin Morrisey in August 2016, and James A. Lombard and James Cuggy in 2018. Accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2016.070 and 2018.094.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact [repository contact information] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact [repository contact information] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Brochures.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Financial records; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Community-based social services.; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; Cudahy, Dorothy Hayden, 1922-2010; Morrissey, Kevin
- Series I. American Irish Feis Institute, 1950-1959
  Scope and Content Note
  The small collection of material in Series I. American Irish Feis Institute refers to the original name of the Irish Institute and contains the original Articles of Incorporation, correspondence, minutes and membership information.
  - American Irish Feis Institute: Administrative, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Irish Feis Institute: Articles of Incorporation, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Irish Feis Institute: Membership information, 1950s, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Irish Feis Institute: Minutes, 1950-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. General and Administrative Files, 1950-2018
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence and other materials on grants, the Annual Dinner, and guests of honor; notices of meetings and meeting minutes; photographs; files on the Institute's building at 326 West 48th Street in Manhattan; a history by Paul O'Dwyer; information on board members; and corporate documents. The 2016 accretion includes correspondence and financial documents from 1991 to 2006 documenting fundraising efforts and grants awarded by the Institute.
  Material in the 2018 accretion contains files maintained by James A. Lombard as president of the Institute between 2008 and 2018, and by James Cuggy as the vice president during the same time period. The material dates between 1978 and 2018, and consists of correspondence, financial documents, membership forms, minutes, photographs, a history of the organization, and copies of its constitution and by-laws. The bulk of the material dates between 2010 and 2015. Both Lombard and Cuggy's files document grants made by the Institute in support of Irish and Irish American cultural programs, in particular New York University's Glucksman Ireland House. Lombard's files contain bank statements, tax documents, and correspondence regarding the Institute's funds. His files also document award and installation of officers ceremonies through correspondence, planning documents, and photographs. Cuggy's files contain a small amount of material regarding Dorothy Hayden Cudahy's involvement in the Irish Institute, as well as the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians and the United Irish Counties Association. This material dates from 1987 to 2010 and consists of correspondence, newsletters, membership lists, and a dues card.
  - Administrative, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administrative, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative (includes photographs), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Dinner 1955, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Dinner 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Dinner 1957: John F. Kennedy, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Dinner 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual Dinner 1959, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual Dinner 1960: Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. - Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual Dinner 1961: Hon. John T. Clancy, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Dinner 1962: Hon. Sean P. Keating, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual Dinner 1963: Hon. John F. English, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual Dinner 1964: Hon. Francis J. Barry, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual Dinner 1965: Hon. Michael J. Murphy, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annual Dinner 1967: Hon. Robert F. Kennedy, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual Dinner 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annual Dinner 1971: Thomas H. Quinn, Guest of Honor (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual Dinner 1971: Thomas W. Gleason, Guest of Honor, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annual Dinner 1978: Leon and Jill Uris, Guests of Honor (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Annual Presentation of Grants, 2000- (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ballintubber Abbey, County Mayo (includes photographs), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bicentennial: United States, 1776-1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Board: Constitution, By-Laws, Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Board of Directors and Officers, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Board of Officers Meeting, Feb 3, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Brendan Voyage Concert, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Brochures, 1952, 1975, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Correspondence (Department of Buildings), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Easement, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Environmental Registration, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Permits, Lease, Blueprint, 1954, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Sale of, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Sale of, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Sale of - Hiney Ministries - Jews for Jesus, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Sale of - L.B. Kale Associates Ltd. v. Jews for Jesus, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Building: 326 West 48th Street: Sale of to Motion Picture Studio Mechanics, Local 52, I.A.T.S.E. (International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employes), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certificate of Name Change (New York Deparment of State), 1953 (Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS001)
  - Clare Heritage Center, County Clare, Ireland, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Irish Ethnicity, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1966, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Resolutions, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (includes list of Officers), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence - project grants, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence (includes handwritten draft of meeting minutes, undated), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cuggy, James -- Office files, 1978-2016 (Box 7, Folder 1-17)
  - Evacuation Day Celebration, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fundraising, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Gaelic Gotham - Museum of the City of New York, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - History (of the Institute) by Paul O'Dwyer, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Irish American Cultural Institute (St. Paul, MN): Trees for Ireland, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Irish Arts Council (An Comirie Ealaion), 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Irish Freedom Committee, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Irish Network, Inc. (American-Irish Media Organization - Irish Conflict), 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Irish School of Ecumenics, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - James Mulvaney Fellowship in Irish Studies (St. John's University, New York), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - John F. Kennedy Memorial Park: County Wexford, Ireland, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - John Street Methodist Church Plaque, 1967-1983, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Kilkenny: Deed (includes Photographs), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lombard, James A. -- Office files, 1984-2018 (Box 8, Folder 1-15, Box 9, Folder 1-17, Box 10, Folder 1-19, Box 11, Folder 1-13)
  - Makemie, Rev. Francis: Plaque (Bowling Green, NYC) (photographs), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Makemie, Rev. Francis: Plaque (Bowling Green, NYC), 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mayo Martyrs Memorial, Feb 13, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Membership Cards (blank), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Members and Mailing List, circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meeting Notices, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Notices, 1985-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Merriman School / Kilkenny School, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The New York Irish: publication and release I, 1989-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The New York Irish: publication and release II, 1989-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newsletter, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - O'Donnell, Peadar (author), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - O'Dwyer, Paul: Conor Cruise O'Brien Today Show Interview on, Apr 28, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pat Finucane Center, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Patrick O'Sullivan Historical Research Fund, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Irish Institute, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Board Members, Feb 19, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photographs: Various, mostly unidentified, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs: Board Members; Fr. Thomas Conagh, St. John's University, 1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The President Kennedy Memorial Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Stokestown Park House: County Roscomman, Famine Museum, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Tom Paine Award Dinner, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - United Irish Counties Association: List of Affiliated Organizations, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 2016 accretion, 1991-2006 (Box 5)
- Series III. Financial Records, 1953-1997
  Series III. Financial Records includes a cash book from the 1970s, a ledger spanning 1966-1975 and other regular financial reports such as balance sheets. Also included are tax returns for the years 1974-1990.
  - Financial Reports, 1953-1997 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cash Book, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Charters (flights), 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Exempt Status (as a Charitable Organization), 1955-1990 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Ledger, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Rice Account, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Savings Passbooks, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Tax Exempt Status, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Tax Returns, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Tax Returns, 1980-1990, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Series IV. Audio Materials, 1960
  Series IV. Audio Materials includes four reel tapes from the Annual Dinner which featured Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. as the Guest of Honor.
  - Annual Dinner - Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. Guest of Honor - speeches (4 reels) Ask Archivist for permission to use, Mar 12, 1960; Reel 1: a)MC - Jack [no last name] b)Irish Institute President, Sean Keating, introduces panel c)John Conway Reel 2: a)Paul O'Keefe, Deputy Mayor b)Paul O'Dwyer, Executive Director of Institute Reel 3: a)End of O'Dwyer b)Harry Hirschfield, comedian Reel 4: a)End of Hirschfield b)Harry Van Arsdale, Central Labor Council President Topics - Civil Rights, Unions, Under compensation of migrant workers, minimum wage, the Irish (Box 4)
    Reel 1: a)MC - Jack [no last name] b)Irish Institute President, Sean Keating, introduces panel c)John Conway
    Reel 2: a)Paul O'Keefe, Deputy Mayor b)Paul O'Dwyer, Executive Director of Institute
    Reel 3: a)End of O'Dwyer b)Harry Hirschfield, comedian
    Reel 4: a)End of Hirschfield b)Harry Van Arsdale, Central Labor Council President: Topics - Civil Rights, Unions, Under compensation of migrant workers, minimum wage, the Irish
- Series V. United Irish Foundation Records, 1982-2004; 1982-1986
  Historical Note
  The United Irish Foundation was founded in 1976 to assist poor, elderly, needy, or disabled people in New York City. The Foundation aimed primarily to assist Irish Americans but was not limited to this group. Its headquarters were in the Irish Institute of New York's building on West 48th Street in Manhattan. Its Community Action Bureaus in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and Queens participated in the Home Energy Assistance Program (HEAP) and the Federal Surplus Food distribution program, among others.
  Material in this series dates between 1982 and 2004 and documents the work of the United Irish Foundation's Community Action Bureaus in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and Queens. Material in this series includes correspondence, financial material, clippings, reports, grant applications, and photographs.
  - United Irish Foundation Records, 1982-2004 (Box 6)